hey welcome back everybody to the we fix
pain podcast this is episode number 20
with our very own Dr Nick aski doc
welcome to the
podcast all right the topic of this
podcast is you guessed it ask asky right
because we uh pulled our our aarian our
acps and uh came up with five five count
them five difficult tough cases that we
want to pick your brain about how to get
better how to get these cases better how
to treat how to manage those conditions
and at the end of the podcast we have
have H about three or four questions on
specific management advice so without
further Ado welcome to the weix paint
podcast I am your host Dr Dino papis I'm
a sports and Rehab based chiropractor
with arosi out of Austin Texas on the
podcast we focus on health and wellness
related topics with a specific focus on
neuromuscular skeletal care that's
injuries to muscles tendons ligaments
joints fascia bones and nerves that lead
to pain we address topics like
assessment diagnosis treatment rehab and
management of acute and chronic related
injuries we humbly ask you and thank you
for watching our podcast please share if
you like this material we're on Spotify
we are an anchor we are on YouTube at
weix pain podcast and my YouTube channel
which is Dr Dino papus Our Guest Dr asy
is a graduate of the University of
Wisconsin Madison go Badgers and Palmer
Davenport yep he's been practicing at
arosi since 2010 he's been a course
instructor and keynote speaker for
educational conferences for
chiropractors and physical therapists
since
2012 grew up on a horse farm in
Wisconsin he played hockey through
college and he enjoys Trail
ultramarathons traveling with his wife
Marisol is that
correct
okay I'm so sorry it's all good but it's
all Greek to me man yeah yep and playing
with his Kane Corso seus he's passionate
about empowering his patients to get out
of pain and then seize the opportunity
to remain active or be more active and
that's our very own Dr Nick ask you so
doc what's your superhero origin story
how' you end up as a chiropractor how'd
you end up here working for arosi take
AER so I had a lot of sports injuries
growing up and my family was kind of rub
some dirt on it uh I actually had a
bilateral spondy grade one and L5 uh on
S1 that I sustained sometime in high
school and I remember walking up to my
dad going dad my back hurts and he goes
so does mine and he'd just spin on a
dime and walk away so we were that kind
of family but there were some things
that you couldn't just rub dirt on and
um I actually had a a bilateral
dislocation of my mandible uh oh man in
high school because I hip checked a guy
and he did a full flip and caught me
under the chin with the heel of a skate
ah and I had went to a chiropractor the
first time for about an eight 18mon
stretch of walking pneumonia that got so
bad that nobody could fix it and my
Cairo kind of dug into my history and he
changed some things in my diet um
because being a farm kid in Wisconsin
it's like you drink two gallons of milk
a day and you know that doesn't do you
any favors on the on the mucus front um
but he skipped a golf outing on a
Saturday and spent two hours working on
my jaw so I could eat uh and I'm like
all right this dude actually cares about
his people um and I want to go do that
for a living so I spent like two hours a
day in his office as like an independent
study for high school credit um and I
never really looked back I was one of
the few kids in my high school class
that didn't change their mind going
through uh but you've known me for a
while Dino you know that I can be pretty
stubborn and headstrong and um so I'm
not usually a very flippant individual
to where I change my mind on stuff once
I've made my mind up um and then my mom
was an aosi patient before I even knew
what aosi was and she got treated by
Shane Arnold and she's like all right
these dudes like fix this hip thing I've
been dealing with for over a year in a
few sessions you should check him out um
and of course aosi turned me down
because I was still in school uh I was
actually the first new grad that arosi
hired um and so didn't have any bad
habits didn't know anything so that was
kind of my selling point was the fact
that I was a clean slate or just like a
a lump of Play-Doh that they could shape
the way they wanted to uh and glad they
took a chance on me um in I moved to
Texas because that's where aosi was back
then uh and spent the first about year
and a half of my uh clinical career on
the in the Austin Market uh in and then
yeah and so I started in buta uh and
then after 18 months when Shane Arnold
made a transition he handpicked me to
take over his practice uh cuz we have
similar styles of
communication a little bit different
clinical Styles but um his patients got
used to me and they didn't kick me to
the curb and I've been in San Antonio in
the third rendition of the ASC or our
support center uh but that's kind of how
we got here today um I'm fortunate to be
a fairly long tenur member of our team
um and I just I I really do like I do
have to think twice and kind of pinch
myself when people are like why don't
you go start your own thing because you
could easily crush it and I was like all
right I don't want all those
headaches um in it was my stance coming
out of school uh cuz I had already owned
several businesses just in the
construction World um on how much of a
headache it can be to be a business
owner and I knew that my patients would
just get the scraps if I had to be the
bookkeeper HR High fire train staff be
the janitor fight with insurance
companies um schedule people so I knew
that if I had to do all that and then
worry about everything else that I
wouldn't have time to learn and grow and
read and and really develop my clinical
skill set at the speed I was able to to
do it with a rosty because I was able to
delegate everything that wasn't clinical
to people that are much better at
performing those things than
me gotcha yeah I I had the Epiphany a
couple years ago about eight years into
being a private business owner that how
life consuming not time consuming life
consuming it was and uh you know we
ended up moving to to Austin uh and end
up getting a job with the rosty and you
know the first thing I said my wife
after the first year was you know isn't
it nice that uh I I'm able to to come
home and be home and be present a lot
more U because you know you can't put a
value on some of the other things your
practice may or may not collect uh
income but you can't put a value on all
the other things that it weighs on you
for yeah yeah so what we're curious what
part of Wisconsin did you grow up in
about an hour north of Madison so kind
of smack dab in the center of the state
uh if you were to like look at it in
Texas terms it'd probably be about Waco
uh kind of smack dab in the
middle and then where did you go play
college hockey uh W Madison oh I didn't
know that kind of a I was not like all
of our starters ended up playing in the
NHL so I was not near that level and I
only played for two years because Frozen
Sher actually ended my hockey career uh
oh wow was one of the rare traumatic
cases of Frozen shoulder and they say
that pain is the body's request for
Change and it just kept me giving me
less and less subtle hints uh that I was
going to have to change up something
because I was taking like eight vicet in
a day to be able to function and shower
and not fall and uh get to class and it
was it was a miracle that I survived
undergrad let alone pulled a decent GPA
being high as Doctor house for the first
two years but just had to kind of look
in the mirror and go all right am I
going to be a good role model to people
if I'm limping down the hall with a cane
and a rattling bottle of pills in my
pocket probably not and am I going to go
the NHL absolutely not um so kind of Ed
my academic uh scholarship for the
second half of undergrad so it was an
easier decision to make because I didn't
have to pay for school either way yeah
yeah and Wisconsin's a great great uh
great school academically and it's a fun
Dynamic setting which I'm sure you
enjoyed uh I don't know if you know I I
worked in the Big 10 as an athletic
trainer so I made the rounds including
Madison that was one of my favorite
stops and uh my alltime favorite event
Madison was when I got to work the Big
10 wrestling tournament uh Circa 2002
2003 is and uh yeah it's uh fun being
working in the big town and then
wrestling and there's always great going
to Madison for about a week yeah it's a
lot like
Austin yeah yeah um let's talk about
some f five random get to know you
questions here uh so so these are just
coming in off the top of my head um you
ready here we go what book would you
recommend somebody would read
twice um I'm GNA give you two the art of
learning um by Josh
wadkin um and then Mastery by Robert
Green okay and then why Mastery is just
a great book for any clinician on
viewing your field as more of an art
form uh rather than just being a
technician and how perfect can be the
enemy of good and people who get good at
doing this usually have a few screws
loose and they don't like to be confused
they don't like
to um just throw their hands up in the
air and give up so they kind of have an
unhealthy obsession with what they do
and how that contributes to Mastery of a
field um the art of learning is a really
powerful book uh it's an easy read it's
one I reread every year um and it talks
about the parallels between mastering
and learning a physical skill and a
mental skill because weit skin was the
subject that they made uh the movie
Searching for Bobby fiser after his
childhood he was a chess Prodigy he was
beating the Russian Masters when he was
like eight years old oh wow uh but then
it just he got burned out because it
became a job and the pressure got so
much because was so young uh probably
wasn't like biologically mature enough
to handle all of that and just kind of
like didn't like to do it anymore and
then he became an eight-time taiichi
Push Hands National Champion um after
that and he talks about the parallels of
learning chess and learning a more of a
physical Endeavor like
taiichi yeah uh I I think the parallel
that I most commonly see what what
you're referring to is the Youth Sports
prod
that exceptional 8910 they're playing
ahead of their grade and by 16 17 18
they're burned out yeah forget college
sports they may not be functional for
their 20s 30s and 40s absolutely so yeah
um okay how many times during an
ultramarathon do you have to stop to go
to the
bathroom uh usually about three you
weren't expecting that one no but I I
know the answer three usually about
three yeah all right cool uh next
question the superpower uh superpower
that you'd most want to have for you you
personally MRI vision is that right see
through everything yep make it make my
job a lot easier and I'd look a lot
smarter than the way I look now i' I'd
be the Wolverine man mutant healing
Father Time's catching up with me yeah
all right uh describe your personality
by a NHL players style of
play
um I would say that's
tough
um just because like being a hockey
player it's hard to
like size yourself up to other hockey
players personality wise um but I know
my style of play was a lot like marshan
for the Bruins like I was kind of the
the spicy guy that no one wanted to play
against and really got under people's
skin uh so I'd say that's probably the
closest nice nice one of my all-time
favorites I'm a little biased I'm a
Blackhawks guy uh dun Keith Duncan Keith
yeah yeah one of my all fav put lot tons
of minutes tough dude skills Scrappy
yeah exactly not afraid to get dirty not
afraid to put it on the net if he had a
chance to you know hoist one at the net
but yeah y you could skate forever too
that that probably I'm a marathon guy so
yeah for me to be Duncan Keith all right
who would play you in a movie about your
life
uh I would probably hope it wouldn't be
like Bobcat go weight or anything like
that but um I I would I would hope it'd
be something like Ed Norton or something
uh he's one of my favorite actors tent
but I do have some twists of like Daniel
D Lewis when I get a little pissy about
stuff to where it's like oh let's leave
Bill the Butcher alone
yeah yeah and he was pretty solid in uh
Last of the Mohicans too you know his
Warface and everything so I just
rewatched There Will Be Blood uh after
watching the whole killers of the flower
Moon the whole oil tangent I just kind
of like went down that and I was like ah
let's let's get a little bit more Daniel
Day in our lives and and watch this
during an oil change and car maintenance
appointment all right let's get to the
clinical stuff you mentioned it uh
frozen shoulder right what is frozen
shoulder what is it what are we dealing
with so it it can look like a lot of
things in the early stages and it's one
of those critical things that you need
to catch it early to manage it
successfully um so it it's basically
there's not a lot of radiographic signs
floor frozen shoulder in the early
stages other than a little bit of
thickening of the corco chromal
ligament um and you can see some little
dehydrated pouches in the inferior part
of the capsule um but I tell my patients
that frozen shoulder just makes us look
really stupid as doctors
because um it can occur from a endocrine
um imbalance that's why it's a lot more
common in the female
population uh with the the hormones
storm that people go through it's very
common in menopause per menopausal women
um they actually released a study this
year saying that they've seen a 2.5 fold
increase in frozen shoulder during covid
uh it was actually added to the long
covid uh set of
symptomatology um and it's usually I
didn't see it at all in a vaccinated arm
um it's usually in the side they didn't
get their their shot in suspicion why uh
no clue really but most people elect to
get vaccines in their non-dominant arm
um so this was in a lot of females on
the right side right hand dominant um
but the the Hallmark signs are active
versus passive range of motion in the
early stages like if you can take
someone passively up to in into internal
rotation or end range of flexion and
abduction it's probably not frozen
shoulder but if you feel like you're
kind of hitting that hard end feel
passively kind of doing like I kind of
do like a a passive inferior Glide of
the humoris and if it feels like it's
Tommy boying up and like pulling the
shoulder up with it with that upper trap
hunching up um I'm like we got to assume
that this is the most the more serious
clinical thing and treat it like it's
early St frozen shoulder and not just
assume that it's a subacromial btis or
an impingement like set of symptoms uh
because the cost of missing a frozen
shoulder in that first four months is is
quite High because then you're just kind
of like riding it out in the side car
with the patient to let time uh because
you once it locks up there's not a whole
lot of Magic Bullets that will unlock it
until it just kind of makes up its own
mind to
unlock so uh to reiterate kind of what
you said you see a pretty significant
loss in a couple different motions the
first is uh your active and passive
motion are roughly about the same
abduction is kind of what you were
describing do you see uh loss of
rotation external internal rotation
prior to the
abduction um usually you'll lose the
abduction first and then the internal
rotation is usually the last thing to
unlock and lock um like you get people
to where you get them up to where they
just are missing that last 10% of
abduction and flexion but they can they
kind of have to do a parlor trick uh to
get their hand behind their back to tuck
in a shirt or get a bra on and off yeah
you see them kind of roll their body
forward and kind of jimy their arm up
that's also why they get a a kind of a
refractory uh second secondary tennis
elbow uh when they start to lose that
rotation because they have to get more
motion uh from the periscapular area in
the scapular thoracic joint as well as
at the elbow because they're they're
faking internal rotation with uh end
range pronation and wrist flexion to get
their arm behind their
back um why does this process occur why
why does the shoulder
freeze like I said only like most of
them are endocrine driven uh only 5% of
them are
traumatic uh you see them a lot in
postsurgical cases because it only takes
about four pounds of P to a force to
dislocate the shoulder when someone's
under
anesthesia especially some of these
bigger bariatric procedure patients uh
that they can be quite the load to move
from table to table if you don't have
all those high-tech hoverboard like bies
that you put people on
um but you do see it like I said it
makes us look like idiots because you
can see it after uh an infection or a
virus or a flu shot or there's a lot of
different things that can cause it um in
that same study I read about covid
having an
uptick um corresponding to the two and a
half times increase in frozen shoulder
um they found that patients that have
been diagnosed with clinical depression
are eight times more likely to get
frozen shoulder and have a poor outcome
on their resolution so like anything
there there there is a bioc psychosocial
component to all the things we manage um
there are some genetic markers that
predispose people um to get frozen
shoulder and those are usually I I it
was a bunch of letters and numbers that
I never memorized but it's the same gene
that kind of predisposes people to
pyron's
contracture uh and plants are
fibromas um so they just have a genetic
propensity for their their fascia to get
a little gnarly and too are they more
likely to like in that subclassification
for scarring like a keloid as well I'm
not sure if it's on the same um in that
same ballpark because I I look back and
I can't IM I can't remember seeing
frozen shoulder in a ton of
African-American patient which are
usually more of your keloid
formers um so I doubt that it's in that
same neighborhood but it'd be
interesting to
see Nick sometimes when uh I've seen
frozen shoulder I've seen a case series
out in the literature and anecdotally
over the course of the year uh years
I've kind of had a couple things that
have been diagnosed as frozen shoulder
and you kind of dig around and you you
look through the history and the exam
and you say I'm not buying this one
um can you speak to other differentials
that would have the U presentation yeah
it's frozen shoulder but when you start
to get into the nitty-gritty your exam
your history you're not buying it uh a
common one that kind of gets labeled as
frozen shoulder because of its
non-traumatic nature and its propensity
for the
demographic uh that it goes after is
like calcific tendonopathy of the
shoulder um because it kind of goes
after the same population with females
with thyroid disorder in their 40s and
50s and
60s um that's the most common one that
all kind of bite on and go okay this is
not developing like a frozen shoulder
and then we do an an image and see oh
like you have calcific tendonopathy in
your shoulder that's why this is kind of
sucked and it hasn't resolved or
progressed at the the same speed as we
would expect from a frozen shoulder
which is like just our our goal when we
get someone early on is to keep it from
locking up if we can and there's kind of
mixed literature of getting a steroid
shot or a PRP shot in the shoulder early
on in the first three to four months I
don't find that that's productive if you
pull the trigger on it when someone's
had it for six or eight months uh and
and the doctor's probably going to bend
a bunch of needles trying to get it in
there
anyways okay
I uh there was a case series years ago
that mentioned uh looking at the spinal
accessory nerve where it exits here like
an entament of the spinal accessory will
produce an abduction that hiking of the
shoulder and then you start to run out
of real estate uh in the glenohumeral
joint where it starts to bang up against
things and there was another uh
differential piece that I read that it's
possible in some you may have super
scapular nerve uh entrapment somewhere
in the posterior and I often find
they're very sensitive um those are
actually kind of amable to the things
that we do so sometimes I go sniffing
around and you know I'll either start
working on the sem and scalings or I
start mobilizing the the super scapular
nerve you know kind of getting them into
this position like a pin and strip and
it doesn't often do it but every now and
then I get one of those cases that will
respond when they were told they had
frozen shoulder so I was wonder if you
had any any tidbits like that
yeah like another Hallmark factor that I
found and this is just anecdotally I
haven't seen it in any literature is if
you on the fence on whether something's
frozen shoulder like early stages and
kind of that early freezing
phase um and you're kind of coin
flipping on whether it's an impingement
or a
btis is if supinatus is five out of five
no pain posterior cuff five out of five
no pain
but their subscap is slightly weakened
and painful uh that's another thing that
I found is a very um handy clue to use
for that um just knowing that it's
frozen shoulder and then I have the talk
with somebody to set the realistic
expectations that this is just really
going to suck like it's I'm not going to
treat them three days apart because I'm
like would you go get your haircut every
3 days they're like no I'm like well
it's kind of like that and I'm just here
to get you through plateaus and
progress uh and kind of put the
accessory fires around the neck and
periscapular area and the lateral elbow
out before they become projects for me
to work on along with the shoulder
itself Nick when do we initiate a trial
of care with these patients versus when
do we say hold we just need to wait this
out when do we say with these folks hey
let's send you to the
orthopedist uh if it's in that first
three four months I send them to the
orthopedist day
one um because a I want a second set of
eyes on their case in case I'm off base
uh but I usually catch them before the
ortho will I've had some disagreements
with some of the shoulder specialists in
town on whether it's frozen shoulder or
not uh and I don't fight with them I
just let time prove me right because I'm
usually
spot on with my instincts but I usually
co-manage these fairly early because if
it does lock up on your watch who gets
blamed for it uh if you lose track of
them and they end up in an ortho office
on their own accord then that Ortho is
going to be like they should have sent
you over here earlier like this wouldn't
have locked up if I got an injection in
there early um but in the ones that are
not appropriate to send to an
orthopedist because it's been too
chronic I tell them like once we've
showed some competence in your exercises
you can get a little bit of sanity and
relief uh and you've showed competency
on being your own doctor for this then
I'm going to cut you loose and you come
in when you need to um because if I
can't predict when you're going to need
me I'm not going to like try to guess
and just schedule something for the hell
of it like I tell people if I'm your
GPS uh and we're going to El Paso it's
my job to get you on to 10 because I
know you're not going to get lost very
easily and we may be seven hours from El
Paso when I let you go on your own uh to
where a lot of these frozen shoulder
cases are like that or we may only be a
couple exits away from El Paso because
the patient's 95% better but I tell
people like if if you're 100% on your
last visit I kept you one too many
visits can you once you initiate an
early trial care month one month two
month three can you uh keep somebody
from the downward spiral or are you more
so trying to manage the fact that they
won't bottom out like what's your
thought about initiate trial care they
do feel a little bit better are you
telling people like we can keep this
from going south from you know freezing
to Frozen and you don't even need to go
into thawing or are you just saying it's
going to be a softer Landing it'll still
be a thud but a softer Landing how do
you how do you explain that I just tell
them I'm like this is a a nonlinear
process and you're going to gain range
of motion back way faster than you lost
it um it's going to be once the thawing
phase initiates like I got all my range
of motion that I lost in three years
back in one
day um and there was no Rhyme or Reason
behind it um so I tell them like these
don't last forever but we just have to
keep banging The Rock and doing the
things that are helping
and because there's really nothing else
out there like you're not going to send
them for a an mua where they have to do
daily therapy afterwards anyways yeah
that's the uncommon unspoken about thing
about mua most people assume they just
walk in they put out they stretch them
under anesthesia they do a little
manipulation good to go and the answer
is no typically the protocol is you
manipulate them consecutively like three
or four days a week and then you send
them for physical therapy for six weeks
after after that's the fallacy yeah and
when people know that there's no easy
way out it's like all right like we're
stuck with the the slow boring diet and
exercise version of fixing this because
I'm like if there was a Magic Bullet
that I could send you somewhere and they
would have the magic way of fixing this
uh like you'd already be on your way out
the door but if I know what's going to
happen when I send you out into the T
and it's going to be a very frust rating
an
expensive uh process I'm going to
protect you from that but most people
when you lay that out in an informed
consent conversation and go I'm it's my
job to tell you what you need to hear
not what you want to hear um people
generally are are bought in and they
accept the fact that you have their best
interest in mind and you're trying to
protect them from either a really
arduous process that's going to cost
them a lot of time and money and not
yield a better outcome um and you're
trying to protect them from people that
may take advantage of them because with
conditions that don't really have an
easy fix you see a lot of snake oil
salespeople that come out of the
woodwork like with diabetic neuropathy
and all these other things like there's
really no easy way to fix it or resolve
it so you have all these guys with their
footbaths and lasers and homeopathic
remedies like um trying to Air and
Rogers these people and it is not a
productive thing and if your patient
doesn't have a healthy amount of
skepticism or doesn't ask questions they
could get taken for a ride and I don't
want to Aid and Abed that uh to
happen last uh last little bit on this
subject you mentioned and I think what's
a really undervalued piece of this the
metabolic healing component thyroid
blood sugar regulation blood pressure
regulation um autoimmune disease these
are absolutely critical and I think in
msk medicine underappreciated and
undervalued to what end do you discuss
it in office what advice do you give do
do you refer out to like functional
integrated medicine or or back to to
Primary Care how do you discuss manage
the the endocrine metabolic piece which
I think for a lot of people is something
that we're not very comfortable with in
nmsk medicine so I tell people yeah this
situation sucks but you've also ignored
a lot of check engine lights to get you
here uh to where if this is the one
check engine light that you can't put
electrical tape over uh it could be a
life-changing moment for the patient in
a good way to uh change their diet up
get more regular blood work with their
doctor actually get a freaking primary
care doctor so they can have someone to
manage their complex health issues so
that's something that I sit down with
people and go hey I'm not your
endocrinologist I am not your primary
care physician I am not your internist
but you do need those things and if you
don't have them I can link you up with
people that I do trust in those fields
uh to get the proper care that you need
and we can use this as the kind of um
the blessing in disguise that it got you
to actually change your life up uh cuz I
had a lady with a shark hot foot and and
like I knew that the X-ray was going to
look like popcorn before I even did it
um and I was like what's your A1C and
she's like I don't know and her wife
looked it up and it was
14.6 ouch ouch I'm like you do realize
that the five-year survival rate of
somebody who has an A1C that
elevated uh you got about an 80% chance
of dying inside of five years so this we
can view this ankle as a hindrance or we
can view it as your life-saving angel uh
that got you to change your life up
because this lady was in her late 30s
and she actually changed her diet up
because she's like oh just get surgery
I'm like no surgeon's going to even let
you in the front door with an A1C of
14.6 because you're going to get a
gangrenous ulcer on your foot and you're
going to lose it yep yep that's a good
way of framing it sometimes there's an
opportunity and opportunity cost and the
opportunity for her is your foot's just
a cue that your life style is a big
problem and uh you know with regards to
the foot you know muscoskeletal pain can
come and go but if you have this big
elephant you know the white elephant in
the room or the big hairy elephant in
the room or whatever yeah that's that's
an important part of your your being on
this planet survival
basically um let let's flip this a
little bit the second most common
question that we got from our Ary
colleagues was the topic of tendinitis
and tendonopathy
so ttis
tendonosis what's the difference and how
do we treat the osis how do we treat the
itis so the itis is the acute stage of a
tendonopathy where it's more of an
inflammatory process uh where you kind
of have to play firefighter to get the
inflammation down uh before you play
arson investigator because a lot of
people will alter their movement
patterns based on a response to pain so
you kind of you can get your you can
kind of get lost and make some faulty
assumptions and logical fallacies if
you're treating your exam as a 100%
valid from a functional testing
standpoint when someone's in a bunch of
screaming acute pain um because they're
going to alter their movement strategies
and their variability of movement in a
response to protect the area um and then
the tendonosis is more of the chronic
presentation which is more of a um lack
of resources type of a situation to
where you have less nutrients for repair
less blood supply a more necrotic
environment to where it's not um or a
more esic environment uh where you have
less uh vascular Supply to an area and
it's just more of like a um a a
condition that you have to load the
tendon in a somewhat uh safe pain level
of four or less to get adequate blood
flow to that tendon and what people
don't realize is you're not you're not
going to see a lot of structural changes
in the tendon when it hurts versus not
hurting uh and the concept in
tendonopathy management is treat the
doughnut not the hole um because you're
probably not going to fix the lesion and
the tendon uh but you can increase the
cross-sectional area of the tendon so
that lesion that is the same size is
less of a percentage of the whole with
the tendon being a more robust larger
tendon with better blood supply our goal
is not to be the the chip and Joanna
gains of people's tendons uh and make
them look very different we just want
them to handle activities of daily
living and loading and be more robust
and strong and that is a process like
you're not going to get strong in three
visits um your strength gains in three
visits are more from pain reduction and
threat reduction and um and you're just
going to have a better handle on what's
going on people don't think they have
elbow cancer or heel cancer and they're
like okay I'm safe I'm being helped out
through this process and it's kind of
like when you start strength training
you get those big novice gains and those
are more from neurologically driven
gains than they are from muscle
hypertrophy gains unless you're taking
the the spicy
creatine uh that is going to help you
get gains faster uh but that's not a
natural way of the body laying down
tissue and so I tell people like the
same thing with the GPS analogy it's
like this all the studies on loading
Achilles tendons are done over 16 to 24
weeks I'm not going to keep you around
here for 16 or 24 weeks but if we know
that you're on the path and you're not
going to need a lot of external guidance
to keep you on the path then we're going
to cut you loose and let you finish it
up on your own and most people are are
amendable to that they're like okay that
sounds good I don't expect you to take
me to my house and tuck me in like they
just want an Uber drive to the front
door especially with the holiday parties
M man get get the Uber right now right
yeah a little too much spicy eggnog and
we got a problem yep so uh I'm going to
reiterate some really important points
um uh for for our a audience and for our
listeners he talked about blood flow
blood flow and blood flow is key and
critical because of all the the soft
tissue structures in the body muscles
tendons
ligaments uh joints cartilage some of
the worst blood flow to a soft tissue is
the distal portion of the tendon right
so uh there's no way to expedite or
speed this up and the answer to the
question is the more you mobilize it the
more blood flow you have but you're
still feel uh pushing a piano up a hill
you can get to the top it's just a slow
process step by step by step so um if we
have to predict tendinopathies and you
talked about the literature from the
start to the end of it assuming we're
starting a loading program today it is
2023 when can I feel the initial
benefits of a loading program when am I
in the middle phases and when will I say
hey I'm 90 95% go back to the gym and
crush it give me the time frame
so it depends on what that person's
demands on their body are if they're a
professional athlete and they have to
jump out of the gym and they have a a
cranky Achilles that's going to take
longer than if someone just wants to
walk with their their friends in the
park because with those you don't have
to really belabor the fourth phase of
rehab for a tendon which is more P
plyometric and Ballistic loading because
they don't need that a lot in their
their normal daily lives but a pro aete
may be in that phase four of their
plyometric loading for uh four to six
weeks until they get that last little
bit out of there um so in general I tell
people like yeah you're going to feel
good enough to live your life in three
to four weeks uh for most of these
things but it's not going to be what we
would stamp as resolved for like that
amount of months not
weeks so I just give people guidelines
of like if the pain is dull achy fatigue
or throbbing and less than a four and
you recover inside of 24 hours that is a
good thing because you just got stronger
you got some loading in you got some
exercise in that was great for you
physically physiologically and mentally
to build confidence in that injured area
but if the pain is Sharp Shooting
stabbing nervy and higher than a four
and it FL it flares you up for multiple
days that doesn't mean that we develop a
fear avoidance behavior of that activity
we just mean that at that snapshot in
time you are not ready to do that
activity yet and it was outside of your
functional envelope of what you were
able to
tolerate because what people get into is
they they Hopscotch The Sweet Spot like
they do nothing because they're
scared and then they blow it out of the
water with the level of activity that
injured it in the first place and then
they get really discouraged and pissed
and then they rest it again and and then
they go do the same amount of loading so
their brain starts to view all activity
as poison and not
medicine but the difference between
medicine and poison is in the dosage so
you just need to teach people how to
think like that and then you know they
are not going to like wander off course
when they are not under your care plan
for the last visit to what we would
stamp as resolved Finish Line these in
our in our office what where I I'll
treat them three or four sessions
hopefully just to put some of the acute
symptoms down and what I'll say to you
is I'll follow up with you in office at
about 30 to 45 day intervals and all I'm
doing is bringing them back reassessing
them seeing if they can tolerate more
load and force and updating their home
program and I will tell them depending
on the length of how how long this Tenon
opathy has been there this will be
anywhere between four months of a
loading program up to about 16 months
and I'll set the expectation the more
chronic it is the longer it's going to
take to get to get better the more acute
that we have it we can shut it down and
modulate that and you can see some
initial benefits within approximately
three to four months and that's what I
I'll tell from the time frame I think
you bring up an important Point too when
you start talking about exercise and
Tenon base exercise we are all products
of when we are uh done with our training
never give a patient an exercise that
will make them uh work worse and then
you will Define worse as producing pain
it's completely different in a
tendonopathy
right so so go ahead go ahead I use you
need some discomfort in the tendon
because I tell him Arnold didn't win
titles with pink dumbbells like his
training hurt but he also wouldn't have
won titles if it hurt too much and he
was injured and he ripped his tendons
off the bone so we need some productive
level of discomfort because you don't
make diamonds without pressure like you
need to load the tendons that's why
Kawhi Leonard didn't stay a Spur because
everyone was tearing their patellar
tendon that year uh and their quads were
slinking up their femur um so he had
such a fear avoidance for loading so as
soon as he hit a one out of 10 shut it
down and he didn't hit that minimal
effective dose threshold level to
revascularize in hypertrophy that
area and and I use a funny little
analogy hopefully this helps our
listeners here I'm a uh you know I I'm
kind of learned from the Neo Conor
school if you make it fun you make it a
song you make it you make them remember
it they'll often remember it I'll use
the words uh 2 three4 no more right like
strengthen it if you're at a 2 three
four you're doing good if we're at five
we're like The BJs man we're staying
alive right staying alive staying alive
right so if it's five and it's trending
up uh I recommend all right we need to
cut it back sets dose reps hold times if
we're five and it's going down to 4 3 2
1 you're doing you're doing right your
body's making that adaptation if we're
78 uh 78 uh 678 I hate so 678 I hate I'm
not strengthening it if your pain is 678
out of 10 10 and if you're strengthening
it and you're a nine to 10 never again
and that's kind of my moniker and that's
kind of My slogan that I
utilize for this uh concept of
tendonopathy
234 no more five Staying Alive 678 I
hate nine and 10
never yeah so um what what I end up
doing is I end up talking to patients
about pain and loading tendinopathies
with pain and I use a kind of funny
little analogy and the analogy looks
something like this it's like two three
four out of 10 no more and if I'm five
I'm like the B's man I'm staying alive
right and what does that mean if I'm
five and I'm trending up got to bring it
back down if I'm five and I'm going down
to 432 one thumbs up and if I if I had
six out of 10 six seven eight I hate and
nine and 10 never again never doing that
one again and it's a quick little easy
way to to kind of get in my patient ears
it's okay to train with pain in fact we
want it for or below like you said if
I'm five I'm kind of monitoring five
becomes four thumbs up five becoming six
we need to back it back
down yeah that's great you mentioned
four phases of of tendon rehab um you
mentioned the last phase the dynamic the
ballistic will reload it in a fast rapid
cycle really quickly and abruptly like
your plyometric what are phases though
one two and three of your your algorithm
for rehabing attended so these are
Concepts that can be debated based on
whether it's a lower limb or Upper Limb
tendonopathy because you have all these
schools of thought of these Experts of
um the the preference for heavy slow
loading
versus um Ecentric or concentric or
isometric but the kind of the basic
protocol that I look at for people is we
use isometrics more for the research
driven knowledge of of that we know they
have an analgesic effect so that gives
the patient kind of a 45 minute
ibuprofen doing a 30 to 45 second
isometric contraction of that particular
area so it gives the patient and
empowers them and kind of reduces the
threat um and then you can progress them
into Ecentric loading programs as the
threat to movement is lowered with the
isometric load loading and then you can
get them into a more concentric driven
rehab protocol and then you Fork off
into the ballistic plyometric and sports
specific loading uh so that you can get
the person ready for their sport or
their hobby or their
activity um so let's take an Achilles
tendonopathy for instance like I would
have them just do like I like isometric
step holds
or we have them just kind of hover their
heel up with a dumbbell on their knee to
hit that Solus
component um and then we'll progress
them into some
Ecentric um heel drops uh and the setup
on that would be different based on
whether it's a
midbelly uh tendonopathy or it is a
insertional tendonopathy on where you
stop at neutral or you can go into a
negative angle uh and then you would
just give them the the concentric and
Ecentric piece in that third phase and
then you develop some more like um lower
load hopping strategies for that Final
Phase um and some people aren't ready to
jump rope yet but you can easily get
someone in a glute bridge and they
elevate their heels and then they just
kind of hgo on their foot when they're
laying on their back um and then that
integrates that ankle hip axis and gets
them talking together because there was
probably a bunch of uh breaks in the
signal that preceeded the
injury uh and loaded the gun so to speak
so you're kind of covering all your
bases on that
progression yeah I agree oftentimes in
these Tenon opathy we focus solely on
the on the area of pain but at some
point in time we need to assess the
kinetic chain for why why the Tenon
misbehaved in the first place doc how do
we get in for a progressive loading uh
because this is a lot of patient I need
you I need you more than you need me so
how do we get the Buy in how do we get
the patient to be a willing participant
in a long program of uh rehab that is
painful that uh the time frame of which
is uh not quite Crystal Clear when
they'll get that magic word resolution
how do we get the Buy
in I get it basically because I know
what their alternatives are um and their
efficacy and they don't like they think
that oh like I'm comparing this to doing
nothing and this doing all this work
that may be painful or uncomfortable and
there's a delayed gratification of four
months uh it becomes a really gnarly
Stanford marshmallow experiment uh of
delaying gratification to get another
marshmallow but if you tell them like
all right like
these are your options for this like I
could send you for a steroid injection
that's going to be really awesome in the
short term but you have a higher
instance rate of rupture whether it's
around the elbow or the Achilles um and
in three months that's going to wear off
and you're going to be right back in
here listening to me
anyways and same thing with oral
medications um if there is another
Avenue that's evidence-based I'm going
to let them know that that is avail
aailable to them but I'm like you didn't
lay on a table like with meat like
you're a piece of meat with eyes and
create this problem you're not going to
lay on a table and get someone to
passively fix it for
you so if they know that the the grass
is not greener on the other side of the
fence and there's a bunch of like
landmine dog turds in the in the yard on
the other side of the fence they're more
likely to hang out with you in your yard
and you're not being deceitful you're
just making them aware
that there's a reason you're taking them
on as a patient even though it's going
to be a frustrating process for
everybody involved because you're
sharping them through your process and
if you believe that your process is the
most value based for the patient and
will give them the most permanent
solution for their problem or at least
the highest chance for it then you need
to explain it like that because if you
know the person's in the right place but
they don't know
or they're kind of in the middle of
their doctor shopping it's going to be a
very contentious relationship that's
going to be frustrating for all
involved yeah I usually try to at the
end of the first consultation if I sniff
chronic tendonopathy I'll lay all the
options out on the table the pros and
cons and like you explained we have the
least invasive but the most active you
have to be a willing participant and the
outcomes long term are significantly
better with a progressive strength
training program but it's labor
intensive you got to do the work but the
the significant negatives of the the
cortisone injections the surgical
management and all that are to the point
where you know um I don't want to say
you have to be a fool but you really
have to think twice about about those
because the outcomes are longterm not
any better so like you said delay
gratification can you wait for this to
be effective your outcome will be better
long term and if you can't you want to
go water skiing in Tahiti or you know
your hik the dolomites in Italy or
whatever maybe you take the short-term
thing but over time no it ain't going to
do it so we have to temper their
expectations because they feel great
walking off the table after a quarter
Zone injection for tenant opathy but you
have to pay the tax collector at some
point in time and I I do tell people I'm
like some of this is motivated by Pro
Sports um like Adrien Peterson is the
bane of the existence of every knee
orthopedist on the planet because of how
fast he came back from his ACL repair
but it's like all right you're a
60-year-old lady with a BMI of 37 like
you're not going to come back at the
same speed as that freak who did nothing
but rehab for six months and then a lot
of these decisions for patients are
driven by the standard of care written
up by the third party payers and a bunch
of Hospital
administrators in the athlete time
timeline like when Tua got the tight RPP
procedure on his ankle to play in the
national championship that was driven by
million doll donors and boosters not a
thirdparty payer or determining the
necessity on when to pull that trigger
I'm like JJ Watt didn't have to get all
those surgeries but he did it based on
the timeline of a team in a general
manager making those decisions they're
business decisions and business
decisions are not not always in lock
step with what we know is evidence-based
or standard of
care yeah and um Aaron Rogers has been
the bane of my existence as a Bears fan
and he may turn out to be the bane of
the existence for Achilles tendon repair
procedures so yeah those internal braces
are going to change a lot of surgical
interventions but that internal brace is
very strong but if he comes back too
quick he is going to get like a sloppy
elongation of his Achilles tendon and
it's not going to be able to store as
much potential energy and it's almost
going to be like cracking the whip to
where there's too much slack between the
train cars and it it's probably not
going to rupture again but it could very
much limit his production in future
years and long term if he rushes back to
a team who has no prayer of making the
playoffs yeah all right let's flip base
here we talked about tendonitis we
talked about frozen shoulder third bane
of the existence of our acps planner
fasciitis and planner fasciopathy what
is the planner fascia what does it do
planter fascia I explain is the leaf
spring of the body uh it helps you
buffer force and ground reaction force
from the ground um in planter heel pain
I tell people like um we start locally
but we have to zoom out globally to kind
of catch some other things that could be
causing it
uh all the way up to the hip and the low
back um because if you don't have
adequate hip extension you're going to
have a more bouncy prancy Pony gate
because you're getting more of that
terminal
stance um kind of forward progression uh
from the gastr Solus complex and not
from the glute uh just due to the
protective nature of the body if you
have too much anterior hip tension and
you can't get extension of a a pelvis on
a fixed femur um with the just due to
restriction in the anterior hip you're
going to have more of a calf dominant
strategy that's going to pick the scab
on the heel um and irritate things uh
some people will just get like fat pad
atrophy as they get older that's kind of
the the crash pad for the heel um and
what people don't realize is the the
calanus is more like uh one of those
it's more like one of those Big Blob
things you see at summer camps where big
fat dad will jump and launch a kid into
the water um like the people think that
the calanus has the bone like the
density of a rock but it's pretty
deformable because the cortex is not
very thick um and that's why if you
pinch the sides of the heel and it hurts
underneath it's like yeah you got a
stress fracture of your your calanas
those are those are missed a lot and
that squeeze test is not very difficult
to do but I tell people we test um more
like big toe extension uh ankle dorsy
flexion hip extension internal rotation
of the hip um before we go elsewhere
just to kind of make sure that we have
the
necessary um kind of implements in the
Swiss army knife so that you're not left
out in the woods without the one you
need
yeah I I agree especially when it comes
to the fat pad and then the calcal
stress fractures now my diagnostic
cluster is you know if I get planner
fascitis tensile it can't handle tension
uh that's when you get the wind last
test or you have them to walk and it
hurts you my opinion is you treat those
like a tendonopathy progressive
strengthening is the name of the game
but you if you start to hear on the
planner fitis hurts them and it's worse
first thing getting out of bed or moving
around after sitting for a period of
time ischemic you mobilize the heck out
of that sucker you bring in blood flow
but when you start to get impact impact
impact what's impact it bothers me more
on heel strike walk on your heels nope
don't want to do it you squeeze the
calanus and you pound on it you start to
get impact mechanism that cortex of the
bone down there is susceptible in the
fat pad underneath then it becomes like
you said protecting the bone whether
it's cushion or whether it's confirming
with an MRI so yeah there's some things
that live down there that are not not
very nice not very um not very good for
patients yeah um we talk about uh the
the uh opposites the differentials uh
here of stress reaction fat pad atrophy
um what else lives uh in the planner
heelal uh you could have like a tarsal
tunnel syndrome uh baers nerve
entrapment um you could have just a uh
an S1 redic um in those are um like I
don't see it like an S1 ridicul apathy
that that's the only uh pain site I have
seen it in the past but my more common
differentials are like uh posterior
tibial tendonopathy as it Scoops around
the medial side um you can get like a
flex or alicus longus tendonopathy
um there there are some other things
that live in the heel um but sometimes
the the testing is not perfect so it's
kind of like a knee meniscus or shoulder
laum it's like if they have a million
tests for something chances are those
tests are not very valuable in isolation
and they suck and it's just kind of a
strength and numbers game um but if
people don't get better on the timeline
we expect uh then it's like all right
let's start doing some like neuro
diagnostic testing or Advanced Imaging
um but a lot of times my initial test if
I feel like I'm kind of getting off
course would be all right let's confirm
that we have a chronic thickening of the
planner fascia with an
ultrasound uh and kind of visualize the
nerves and see if there's some uh
swelling around the nerves there so we
can get a little bit more Direction
before we just start throwing money
around on a lot of these Advanced
Diagnostic
testing there's a Litany of treatments
and if you go on YouTube or Google or or
you know your local running group who
Guru uh people will throw anything and
everything at planner fitis and planner
fasciopathy so I'm going to list a bunch
of treatments and therapies and I want
you to match uh I want you to match who
responds to this type of treatment what
what criteria do we know that they will
respond to specific types of treatments
as well because there's a a whole real
quick if we can get like one or two
sentences so who is the patient that
will respond to manual therapy the
things that we do you know the the
myofascial release tissue manipulation
the active releases the grasons of the
world which who is the patient planner
fitis that will respond to manual
therapy usually the people that respond
the best are goal oriented like athletes
uh not necessarily a super high BMI with
bilateral heel pain um and people that
you know it's like all right
that we got our positive like tow walk
windless that kind of thing they they
tend to respond fairly well um versus if
the heel pad is bruised or atrophied
it's like all right we're going to show
you how to tape this stuff up
and kind of put some protective
cushioning or your little house Crocs uh
just to keep from banging that thing
into the concrete
floor okay who who is the patient that
will respond to we don't need to do
manual therapy we just need to rehab
them um more of the the patient base
that may be bilateral or they have a BMI
thing that's contributing to the problem
in more of the um the other cases that
we talked about to where it's like all
right these are more of the um
tensile loading things to where it's
like all right we just need to stretch
this thing out it doesn't necessarily
need a a super long load loading period
they just have they just need to be beat
up like a baseball glove once or twice
and then they just reinforce that at
home dry needling I've had some patients
inquire and ask me about dry needling
for planner fasciitis who do we want to
send to dry needling or who should we
give information you know dry needling
may be for you uh dry needling if you do
have some carryover into the deep
posterior compartment of the leg uh or
you just need some some one who's got
like if you see their fourth and fifth
toes are kind of like curling
underneath um that's a sign of quadrus
Plante weakness uh and that does respond
fairly well to dry needling to kind of
wake it up uh it's almost like a a
painful muscle energy technique uh to
get that quadrius Plante firing and
you'll see like the fourth and fifth
toes are like kind of trying to get
pinned under the third one uh because of
the mechanics of that uh that pivot
point between the bones that are
attached to the the cuboid and the ones
that have their own CA forms so is this
a neurological inhibition or is this
like um like a flexor tendon contraction
where over time the tendon starts to to
go and to go degenerative changes and
you start to get you know like a flexor
tendon but the quadrus plant is it more
so the tendon is it more so the
neurology um I believe it's more so the
tendon and the balance between short and
long flexors and uh and extensors to
where it's kind of the same process that
makes a second toe kind of hammer up uh
because these people have an imbalance
between their their short extensors and
their long
flexors I get some questions about
modalities the other modalities that are
common that we start to see some stuff
on the internet for our Shockwave and
laser therapy for planter fitis who
would be the the person that would most
benefit from either Shockwave or laser
therapy shock wve I'm a big fan of it
and we've had um a lot of patients
respond positively to these
nonresponsive uh stubborn cases of
chronic heel pain um in the laser um in
my opinion laser is for people that want
to waste money um like it does work for
certain things but haven't seen a lot of
concrete positive things that happen
outside of the kind of the placebo
effect of I paid a lot of money to do
this so I want it to
work does the quality of the laser or
the depth of penetration or the amount
of um photons matter or is it more so
the modality Itself by Design and by
nature is just not very
efficacious yeah the the productive
wavelengths of laser
um you have your class three and your
class 4
lasers um and those class 4 lasers are
not going to be really accessible to a
patient on a home basis because they're
prohibitively expensive you see them in
a lot of Rheumatology
offices um that they use them for
treating patients uh I actually have a
class three laser at my house and I've
noticed benefits for uh wound healing
speed and like using it on certain
trigger points points and joints and I
use it on my dog um and dogs don't have
a placebo effect it's like yeah he's
moving around better um and I do notice
that like uh abrasions
lacerations um that kind of thing will
heal up faster using that 830 nanometer
class 3 laser but if you're able to find
a laser on Amazon for 150 bucks it's
like save your money because it's
probably just no more than a laser
pointer or a flash flash light that'll
burn your eyeballs um but it's not going
to be a depth of penetration or a
productive wavelength to affect the
cellular metabolic rate and
mitochondrial function in the area
Orthotics Nick Planet fitis who needs
Orthotics Orthotics are a temporary
intervention for most people if they
don't have a
genetic uh like a super weird shaped
foot or a club foot or uh they can be
helpful for heel pain in adolescence
using like the gel heel cups uh they can
be helpful for people with the fat pad
atrophy long term or you get patients
that they're 90 years old you're
probably not going to change you're not
going to teach them too many new tricks
so it's like all right I could take a
bunch of this 90-year-old lady's money
and not really change that her knees
bang together when she she stands up um
I can just send her to the Running store
and get a rigid orthotic and it will
help out but for most people in the
average demographic that we see heel
pain um I tell people this is a
temporary intervention almost in the
same vein as like a night splint um to
where it's like we want to wear these to
keep from picking the scab as much until
we get the requisite problem fixed that
created the issue
you yeah 100% I'm bored orthotic they're
missing the second word it's called
orthotic therapy uh and most people like
eyeglasses you know your prescription
changes the goal of the orthotic is to
get you out of the orthotic it's
progressively to use less and less and
less invasive orthotic to get you out of
it unless you have a true relevant
keyword structural deformity that you
cannot adapt around uh get you in an
orthotic progressively teach your body
with exercise how to manage how to
perform the Habit that we want phas you
out of it unless you have a true
relevant structural deformity you can't
compensate around hey Nick uh the
injectables cortisone any role for that
in planner fitis or planner
fetopathy if you want to do the surgery
for yourself and rupture it then yes or
if we have those timeline things of like
all right I dropped 20K on this trip to
Machu Picchu in like I don't care what
the long-term side effects are I just
want to enjoy my trip I'm like yeah go
get a shot but don't expect that that
shot's going to fix you because that's
like the star and Mario Brothers like if
you aren't doing anything productive
during that uh period it's like
unplugging the controller when you have
the invincibility star and Mario
Brothers like we want to run our ass to
the end of the level and climb the flag
pole before that thing wears off yeah
100% I agree short term I've had people
like I'm like you said I'm going to walk
uh it's the Camino roale in in Spain and
it's like 4 days away and I was like
find the Orth or or the podiatrist
because Miracles only happen uh you know
at church on Sundays right so yeah and
uh I once had a podiatrist tell me like
you know if you can't get this planner
fascia under control I'm just going to
keep injecting it I was like for what
purpose and they're just like well it'll
feel better and then it'll rupture and
I'm like and then you're going to do
what when it ruptures well I'm going to
recommend an orthotic seems like a
backwards way to prescribe an orthotic
in the first place right like we're
going to destroy the planer fascia then
to prescribe an orthotic to help you
restore your gate mechanics and I'm like
that's a backwards way to prescribe an
orthotic So orthobiologics Hot Topic
these days in uh in uh you know Physical
Medicine who's an orthobiologic
candidate for planner fitis are you
lumping in PRP with that or just the
yeah stem cell and PRP so PRP I've seen
some benefit but that's kind of muddied
by did the patient get better uh from
six weeks being in a boot or did they
get better from the combination of being
booted and injected with PRP because
you'll see that the the planner fascia
when they measure the thickness it will
go down on follow-up exams so it's not
just a placebo effect because it is
actually changing the kind of that
chronic thickening of the insertion of
the planner fascia um in general like
orthobiologics like the stem cell stuff
uh unless you're flying to Panama to get
it done you might as well just inject
dead toenails into somebody because it's
about as effective as that um you don't
have spots in the US outside of three
research sites where they're doing like
legit plur potent uh stem cell
injections um
for um like they're testing it for hip
and knee
arthritis um and they're getting great
results but like guys that want to get
like legit flurry potent stem cell
injections they're flying to Panama to
get it done um yeah in the United States
we uh we can only Harvest stem cells um
from the patient's own body and they
can't magnify the effect so they can't
try to to Tinker with it to increase the
number and the viability of stem cells I
think that's what Nick is referring to
um outside of a research uh specific
approved research clinical trial which
creates a quander because if you're
going to go big big it's go big or go
home and that that's what Nick is
referring to is out of the country they
don't have the restrictions and we're
seeing data from foreign countries that
can Tinker with that for sets dosage
viability I think that's what you're
referring to yes and the the director of
those research studies is actually from
San Antonio Hae Garza he's doing it
through um his Clinic here in town
through T lane and then there's a site
out in Pennsylvania that they're doing
studies with the the NFL Hall of Fame
because he played for the
Saints um Nick last thing is there a
role for surgery in the planner fascia
you know where they snip the uh one of
the bands or multiple bands of the
planner
fascia um I don't see the value in it I
haven't had someone come in bragging
about um how good they feel if they do
get surgical intervention the only
people I've seen that have had positive
surgical interventions for
planner fasciitis or planner fasciopathy
uh is with like a 10x type procedure
which is more of like all right we're
just going to cut you open to do some
some other form of uh pulse wave therapy
that targets the collagen type that is
uh not necessarily consistent with good
healthy tissue uh let's pivot here real
quick uh another topic that drives our
acp's nuts degenerative spine conditions
namely lumbar spond Lois cervical spond
losis what is this condition what is
spondy
losis it is natural aging of the spine
if it's considered what we would say age
appropriate um in it is basically just
gray hair of the spine um after age 35
you can have an old worn out weak spine
or an old worn out strong spine so I
tend to reduce the threat that patients
perceive of them being damaged goods by
saying would you go up to your grandma
and say you have degenerative face
disease because you have
wrinkles uh if the answer is no that's
essentially what like you're thinking
about yourself is like this has been
there for a long time and I tell people
like we're all on a slow march to
stenosis and spondy losis some just get
there faster than others and some have a
little bit more interesting March but it
doesn't necessarily have to be trauma
it's just like all right you've danced
with gravity for 50 years like this
stuff's going to wear out um but when
you get some wear and tear and thinning
of the discs um and like facet
hypertrophy as you get some slack in
some of those ligaments that surround
the disc you're going to put more of a
load on the posterior elements of the
spine being the ligamentum flavum the
facets and then those are going to kind
of wear and tear and wear out um so I
just tell people it's normal like if all
of your pain was coming from spondy
losis and arthritis I wouldn't fix any
back pain patient over 35 because they
all have
arthritis Nick Ro you mentioned a couple
key structures the facets you mentioned
the posterior fibers of the disc you
mentioned the anulus ligamentum fum what
role does the endplate itself I think
the end Plate's kind of the red-headed
stepchild of the movement segment we
didn't know much about it at first and
we don't commonly talk about at least in
my chiropractic curriculum and it's been
an area I've been reading a l a lot on
on modic and endplate changes what role
does the endplate play in spondy losis
you can get some discogenic back pain
from certain modic type changes that I
have to look up on a chart every time
cuz I'm like all right which one of
these is something that we need to test
their blood for cancer and which one of
these is kind of an active uh
degenerative process happening uh and
then which one of these is just purely
benign fatty infiltration things like
that schls nodes um so I have to look
that up every time I do an MRI review
with a patient uh just because I like
there's limited real estate in my brain
and that's something that I'm like all
right I'm just going to GTS that every
time I need to remember it um in like
but if somebody is having uh a modic
change where they have an active
degenerative process happening um we
we're understanding more about some of
these processes in the spine and
elsewhere that like we're we need to
give it a little bit more study because
osteoarthritis of the knee they're
finding is actually uh more of a active
inflammatory process than we thought it
was of just like all right cartilage is
just banging together and it's wearing
out but there is a chemical piece of
that process and that can happen in the
dis space face as well and I've had some
people I know that
happens um even without an image because
they'll their back will feel a ton
better just if they're on antibiotics
for a UTI and they'll biopsy dis
material after a miter procedure and
it'll have like cultured bacteria in the
disc space which is supposed to be a
fairly sterile
environment um so I think that uh the
jury's still out on how much we're going
to go down that rabbit hole but it is
important to note and read that stuff
and not just look at the jelly and the
dut as a just a purely mechanical
process yeah there was a landmark study
in 2010 to 11 like like you referenced
that uh they gave people that had
chronic long-standing generative changes
a course of antibiotics and they tracked
them and they gave a placebo they gave
an antibiotic and you know I think there
was another uh third third group and
they tracked it over time for
symptomatology and uh you know the anti
biionic one actually had the greatest
benefit as compared to a placebo and I I
forget with the third group of that
study which is really eye openening
because we we thought about it once is
just a purely mechanical phenomenon um
so yeah it' be interesting to see where
where that uh research goes um Nick
let's back up here we we talk about H
facet and the disc those are the two big
players what does the and and we just
got ahead of ourselves talked about
modic changes in the endplate what does
the endplate do and what is its
relevance to the movement
segment so the end plate kind of gives
um I view the end plate kind of like um
your your endplate if we look at the
disc is like a microcosm environment the
end plates are basically your pelvic
floor and your diaphragm it gives
something to create pressure um and if
you have a defect there uh to where it
kind of limits the amount of pressure
that the this can buffer and push
against uh it's almost like having a
hernia you aren't going to be able to
pressurize even if it is a small defect
so you're going to have some um excess
micro micro movement in that area if you
don't have a firm ceiling and floor for
that disc to create back pressure on how
do we treat and manage these Lumbar and
and cervical spondy losis conditions
what types of treatments and therapies
or how do we know what what to do in in
uh from our history in our
exam um most of these can be fixed by
balancing out the hips and getting
rotation in the
t-spine because if there's things that
you're trying to use your back as a hip
it's going to bark um and if you're
moving and you're excessively rotating
through the lumbar area which is
designed to get about 3 to 5 degrees of
rotation at a segmental level um in
where the facet orientation in the
t-spine is built for rotation but if
you're a locked up Lego character up
there you're going to rotate through the
your lumbar facets and bad things are
going to happen uh let me throw a pen
here to put the light back
on um but overall um it's just all right
we got to get the movement through the
right
areas um so that we're not aberant
loading the spine or excessively loading
the spine and then we get good movement
so we get them moving well then they
move
often and walking can be a very powerful
activity for that in a in absence of uh
like neurogenic claudication from an
advanced case um or someone who has some
other comorbidities like or Orthopedic
issues that they would have an aberant
gate from those I'm just like you don't
have to do all this crazy stuff you just
need to go
walk yeah walking is a known exercise
which triggers um inhibition if I'm not
mistaken of the disc and inhibition is
pressurization but more importantly it's
hydration lubrication nutrition and just
normal gate patterns restoring normal
gate patterns the ability to walk and
and put a little Force through it can
have significantly positive effects and
it's something so easy we need to walk
for General Health but if you combine
that General Health with spine health
and you say just give me 20 minutes two
to three times a day and that's your
home exercise program psychologically
they'll feel better but physically their
back may feel better too yeah um let me
uh move on with um a couple other
tidbits uh here the last major thing
that drives our acp's Nots peripheral
neuropathy and I think the biggest thing
with peripheral neuropathy neuropathies
is and understanding uh why and how is a
nerve really easy to stir up how does
this happen why does it
happen um it doesn't like anyone who's
bang their funny bone and had some a
little bit of a transient irritation of
their on nerve knows that it doesn't
take a large amount of pressure to make
a nerve
symptomatic um and nerves don't have to
be mechanically or traumatically
irritated they can also become more uh
permeable uh due to chemical irritation
like if you have like an annular tear in
the disc that isn't putting any
mechanical compression and they don't
have any nerve tension findings but you
can tell that the disc is secreting
substance p and making the nerve more
hyperpermeable so there are very touchy
structures um and I don't want people to
get the wrong idea on this but like when
patients come in and they have a nerve
irritation whether it's uh Central
spinal peripheral I tell them like this
nerve is like my wife and if it is not
happy nobody involv is going to be happy
so when we talk about pushing people
through yeah happy life with with
tendons like you need to push people
into a bit of discomfort but I tell
people like especially if I'm adding a
slider glider type of a a thing I'm like
all right this is a very potent exercise
but when added too early in a treatment
plan it can really take us the wrong
direction that we don't want to go so
it's like you you're more um you're more
educated on the McKenzie protocol of
like when you're looking for directional
preference or your mobilizing people
it's like all right we we don't want
this to stay elevated after doing an
exercise or it's just not the right
exercise for you but we need to get some
neurodynamic Glide and slide of that
whole Pathway to get this thing calm
down yeah the key thing I I find is the
during but what you said the after fact
20 30 40 minutes later if it stays
elevated pain loss of function
immobility disability wrong choice right
they get a little bit transient during
monitor it but if it stays and lingers
no you got to back off that pretty soon
so what you're saying is that uh nerves
are easy to sensitize easy to piss off
hard to calm down and they respond to
Mechanical stimuli chemical stimuli
thyroid issues blood sugar issues
blood pressure issues and all these
things chemical stimuli mechanical
stimuli and even bio bio the the
psychosocial component can sensitize a
nerve is that kind of what I'm getting
from that yeah how do we settle them
down
then um first and foremost the question
in the history is how long has this been
the way it is um because if you have a
nerve entament that is giving someone
either motor weakness or sensory issues
or reflex issues that has been
constantly there for 3 years I'm like
that plant's dead no amount of water or
fertilizer or sunlight is going to bring
the dead plant back so why are we going
to waste money and resources trying to
water the dead plant when we've know
it's been dead for three seasons so I
just have to give those people the
unfortunate news that like like not to
look for a solution to something that
doesn't have a solution like we're just
going to have to plan around it if
you've had foot drop for five years I'm
not making it go away yeah if it's kind
of been touch and go and intermittent
and reversible it's like yeah we know
that we can get this thing to calm down
because if you have Windows or positions
or times a day where it does get better
then we know it is a changeable
phenomenon but if like I had a guy that
evolves to nerve Roots out of his neck
and looked like he had a stroke in his
hand I'm like you need to go to Mayo
Clinic and get a tendon transfer because
this is not going to go away because you
you ripped the cord out of your neck
like you rolled your Jeep over and you
ripped two nerve roots in your neck that
aren't no one can reattach
that so it's duration and then some of
these are nightmares like you get
someone that has like paresthesia in
digit four five in their hand um and
it's like all right that could be any of
the eight on their nerve entrapment
sites um going from carpal tunnel gon
cubital tunnel um all the way up it
could be because to manifests on the
allner side usually first could be an
entament there could be a C8 redic could
be something all the way up in the like
the descending tracks of the spinal cord
so it can become a diagnostic nightmare
to where sometimes you just have to
start somewhere and then kind of gauge
the response if if the patient doesn't
have the resources or doesn't elect to
do like a an EMG procedure like you're
not going to do that day one until you
at least
try so they can be a bit tricky but a
lot of them it's like all right if you
use the tools that you learn um a lot of
times you can kind of tease out like
okay is this just sensory is this just
motor um are we getting atrophy uh you
can kind of tease out like at least a
ballpark of where to point the
crosshairs for your
intervention now assuming you have a
patient in the office they have
intermittent let's focus on the the you
know you kind of you kind of went the
route of like a constant numus tingling
burning you got sensory motor deficits
and it's longstanding and we need our
colleagues our Neurosurgical colleagues
our pH physical medicine and Rehab maybe
for the emgs ncvs or neurologists of the
world assuming you have something that's
intermittent comes and goes um and and
and it's lowlevel not so much strength
changes maybe some sensory changes no
reflex changes and you have a peripheral
neuropathy nerves heal what is the time
frame for which a nerve can potentially
regenerate heal or we can start seeing
significant traction towards Improvement
and this is about setting expectations
like our tendonopathy discussion is they
usually heal about a millimeter a day
okay and I'll explain some of these
neuropathy that I know we're going to
get a reversal but I call it a nerve
bruise it's like bruises heal but they
don't there's nothing you can do to make
them heal faster it's just a a waiting
game but if you keep on punching the
bruise it's going to lengthen your
recovery time so we just need to stop
punching the bruise let's transition
here real quick to some simple
management advice so those were the top
five conditions and they were plan ofas
opathy tendonopathy frozen shoulder
peripheral
neuropathies and uh Lumbar spondy losis
and a partridge and a per we had some
questions from our acps on management
advice so give me one one or two quick
little blurbs on the following topic
overtraining syndrome and the two things
that we had on this were how do we
identify it and how how do we tell a
patient you need to stop activity right
because we're in the mindset of we and
part of the reason why people come to us
is because they want to continue to do
the activities they want to do I want to
come utilize us continue to do their
things but there is a time in a place i'
argue for what you need to slow your
role you need to slow down you need to
unload this for a period of time so how
do identify overtraining syndrome and
how when do we recommend hey stay away
stop the stop
recommendation so the first or
hallmarked sign of overtraining is
interrupted
sleep um because you're going to get
blood sugar fluctuations due to the
elevated cortisol levels in a patient
that is
overtraining um and I have a lot of
patients that are overtraining um it's a
difficult conversation to have because
what'll happen is someone will overtrain
and then their cortisol levels cause
them to like the body's not going to
like burn body fat for fuel so these
people gain weight rather than losing
weight with excessive training and you
just need to tell them like all right
why are we doing this kind of try and
get in their head on why and then you
can kind of like set a compromise like a
lot of these people aren't going to go
from cranked up to 11 down to zero but
you at least need to meet them in the
middle somewhere and come to a a a
compromise of how much is too much and
these are the boundaries and the
guidelines otherwise I'm not going to
continue to treat you if you're
self-destructing and not following my
advice uh yeah I I I like that we can
use the uh the watches the monitors the
tracking apps on the phone all of it now
to kind of look for Interruption and
sleep patterns and abnormal heart rate
variability which is a really key
indicator for us and to the point uh I
like what you said I have had patients
over the years that have been
marathoners and have told me I'm gaining
weight despite the high volume of
activity I act and I asked them are you
participating in a majority of your
training runs as scheduled 80 90% yes
and you're still gaining weight yeah and
I use the criteria imminent harm uh if
you're imminent harm of something that
has a negative long-term Health
consequence a stress fracture that turns
into fracture uh you you increase a
metab metabolic cast of blood sugar
blood blood pressure disregulation that
can lead to long-standing problems I
need to tell you to stop everything else
I'm comfortable with modifying the
activity but if you're an imminent harm
it's it's a no-o um cool pain
psychologist one of our acps had a
question management piece when do we
need to bring in a pain psychologist
into discussion and
conversation uh if you can kind of tease
out some stuff in the history that the
patient is going through either a fear
avoidance situation with their sport or
activity or you can tell that things are
not great at home due to a relationship
issue or death in the family or things
like that and then you you can kind of
like I just kind of tell people like all
right pain there is a mental piece uh
and not everyone with depression is
depressed because they hurt some people
hurt because they're depressed and so
these things are really interrelated and
a lot of times you just have to tell the
patient that that is available to them
and just leave it at that because it can
be a touchy situation because uh no one
wants to be told that their their pain
is all in their head and they're crazy
but the patient will usually tell you
when they need that intervention but if
they don't know it's available they're
not going to mention it because they
don't know it's an option next major
question from our uh rosty colleagues um
stopping a trial of care um there one of
the the things that I struggled with
initially at my time at arosi and
sometimes I struggle with a bit now to
be to be quite quite honest and quite
Frank and throw myself under the bus on
this one is you can't fully fix a
patient uh they get better but they
won't resolve they're not quite surgical
they're in this kind of weird Loop of
what to do how to how to do it and
obviously there's a lot of fear worry
and concern on the patients aspect so
how do we treat and manage these cases
that we may not res solve is it changing
the definition changing the mindset
these weird this weird Loop they won't
fully get better but they'll get a
little bit better but we haven't made
expectations how do we manage those
cases I go back to the patients goals
that they set on visit one and a lot of
times we can lose perspective on what
the patient's actually there for because
we set loftier goals for the patient
than they actually have for themselves
so it's like if if you go back to the
their goals that you set for short and
long term and the patient isn't perfect
but you've achieved the goals for like
three visits now it's like it's time to
just have that discussion with the
patient of all right we've achieved our
short and longterm goals this is not
affecting your ADLs you're sleeping
where you weren't before going through
the the progress and tell them like all
right this is how much short we are of
what your view of 100% is but this is
what I think it would take for you to
get to 100% And is the juice worth the
squeeze or are you just okay with
playing the slow game of yeah this may
kind of just may be tincture of time and
continuing to load or do the the rehab
at home but it's not going to require
any more medical interventions because
the medical interventions that would be
needed to get to get to their their
perception of
100% are either cost prohibitive
dangerous or have a higher likelihood of
making them feel worse than they do
right
now yeah I like that I like that and the
thing that you mentioned bringing it
back to the patient right that's why
they're here and if we're at or near or
or getting close to meeting their
expectations and we can't fully in our
mind resolve it it's not about us it's
about about them so I like that bringing
it back to the patient yeah that's a
good one pelvic floor I got a question
from arasy one of our arasy colleagues
about how do we parse out in the history
and exam that low back or an hip or
something like that hip pain or low back
pain or sacr iliac pain is pelvic floor
rather than the muscular skeletal stuff
low back hip or joint um I've sent one
male patient to pelvic floor therapy so
female gender is a big one um females
that have had multiple children if their
symptoms are onset in a
postpartum or after a difficult natural
birth uh if they have Painful
intercourse uh urinary
incontinence um they they like pee
themselves every time they cough or
sneeze uh and they just have this like
waxing and waning like without an
appropriate trigger of what I call
Cousin Eddie back pain it's where it
just kind of Pops up and it's um it's a
it's a problem it always shows up
appropriate that's an appropriate
reference it's it's the 16th of December
and cousin Eddie's coming to somebody's
house here pretty soon full but
those are the main things I look for in
like most of the ones I've sent for
pelvic floor therapy to a specialist who
does it um they get great results um but
you another one of those things is like
the mental health professional you just
have to let them know like hey this
could be a diagnosis of exclusion if we
can get you there to where you feel good
we won't have to pull that trigger but a
lot of pelvic floor PT is cash-based and
it's not always a viable option for
someone who is on a very fixed income or
they're they're doing a lot with a
little bit of money yeah they're trying
to make things stretch uh and some
some's got to go um and the other thing
I think when you prep somebody from a
pelvic floor PT referral that's
important is oh by the way it's going to
be uncomfortable because they may do
some internal things that I am not
legally allowed to perform but it is a
standard part of pelvic floor PT
practice that they would do these things
uh and you have to be prepared for
somebody to perform these things and if
you're even uncomfortable with the idea
then this won't work and then you you
kind of like leave them with that let
them stew over it and if they accept the
referral great and if they don't you
made them aware because if they walk in
and they feel like they're violated and
don't know it it's a bigger problem yeah
and I tell people that in bundled up in
the conversation of why I'm not going to
do
that it's like yeah that's not legal for
me to do and this is what they're most
likely going to do and neither of us
want me to do that to you or show you
how to do it to yourself uh because this
is this is a close on
relationship yeah yeah yeah I remind me
sometime we get together for for coffee
or dinner or beer or something to tell
you about the nice couple that were
French that came to the office sometime
yeah so it's a funny story um last thing
uh we got an excellent question I
believe it's Dr David Smith I think he's
up in Dallas Fort Worth if member serves
me correct career longevity for acps
mental health physical health emot
Health uh what's the best two or three
management management pieces that you
can give to our acps for career
longevity um I've tried to train my
patients to not really lean on me for
administrative stuff that could be
handled through an online portal an app
like even if I have my computer in front
of me to schedule somebody I make them
do it through the app because I don't
have time to schedule or re schedule a
bunch of people I try and create a low
maintenance patient base uh to where
they don't think I'm just bored sitting
around waiting for them to send me an
email or make me fill something out for
their work uh I'm still going to go
through the extra mile and do things for
people but if I can cut down on the
things that I don't have to do uh when
we have a channel for the patient to do
that themselves or talk to one of our
our co-workers or team members that
that's their
job um I'm not going to do that because
it's a death by Thousand Cuts thing with
burnout you don't want to do things that
you don't have to do if there's already
an established system and process for
that um one other thing is like if I can
push an arbitrary amount and fix the
person I push just that hard like I'm
not going to over pressure a patient or
put more pressure on them uh than I need
to to get it to respond um when like I
got to do this for a long time and I
have been doing it for a long time
because that's my strategy is I don't
just like beat the heck out of people I
don't push as hard as I did when I first
started because I can feel things
release and respond and I do spend a
little bit more time on uh examining so
I don't have to just take an Uzi
approach of what to treat I may treat a
more finite area because my exam uh sent
me down that path so I don't have to
like scorched Earth the whole quarter of
this person's body because I had a a
poor exam and I'm just throwing crap at
the
wall yeah I agree think five minutes to
treat two like spend more time in
assessment and understanding the
relevance of different things to to
treat too and then Moder I agree 100%
moderating your pressure because I'm
same way seven years in I use less now
than I did before because I got to
sustain my body over time and then the
other thing too is you can explain to a
patient about bruising and some people
wear it like a badge of honor they
walked out of rosty and get bruised but
if they walk out of rosty didn't get
bruised and got the same result
everybody wins so yeah 100 perc Nick hey
thank you for your time we've been on
quite a bit of time can we sum this up
and and can you give us your closing
thoughts what you'd like to convey to
the masses
and then where and how can people find
you well I appreciate you having me on
uh as far as where you can find me um
I'm on Instagram at kick
asky um you can reach out to me through
there U you can email me um but email
like sometimes it falls through the
cracks uh because i' get so many emails
but overall like I think that if you let
me like assault your here for an hour
and a half uh and you made it this far
uh you're you're probably in a pretty
good spot because you're curious you're
learning you're growing um and just as
you get more experience as a doc you
just want to have the discipline to just
continue to learn and grow and uh early
on I think when you're you're reading
and and digging into material when
you're new 80% of that should be in your
field of subject of like all right
musculoskeletal medicine uh but as you
get more seasoned and you've been in the
field longer that should switch to where
20% of the stuff you read should be in
your field and then 80% of your reading
or research should be uh in fields that
maybe aren't yours to inspire some
creativity and avoid the burnout and the
monotony of just learning about the same
things over and over and over again and
you may get a little bit of creative
inspiration that takes you down a rabbit
hole that was blocked before by reading
um philosophy or a different branch of
medicine or reading um about these
things are that don't necessarily have a
lot to do with what you do for a
living yeah I like that and I listened
to a podcast yesterday about uh burnout
finding purpose in your 40s and I'm in
my 40s now and uh what they said was try
to get out of your discipline and area
of expertise and practice and what you
may find there some lessons that you can
apply to what you do but at the very
least that keeps the Mind fresh right
mind's a very powerful tool propels you
to 100 miles it propels all of us to do
the things that we do at a very high
level doc thank you so much for your
time and generosity and answering all
all of our questions this is the weix
pain podcast number 20 with Dr Nick asky
ask and we are signing off thanks doc
thank you